Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Eugene Berman papers
1926-1975
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Berman, Eugene
6.7 linear feet
The papers of painter and theatrical set designer Eugene Berman date from 1926-1975 and measure 6.7 linear feet. Found within the papers are scattered letters, primarily postcards, from various colleagues including Juliet and Man Ray and Berman's brother Leonid. There are also notes, scattered artwork, printed material, and extensive photographs, many of Mexico.
Provenance
The Eugene Berman papers were donated by the artist's sister-in-law, Sylvia Marlowe Berman, in 1978.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Eugene Berman (1899-1972) worked in New York City, Los Angeles, California, and Rome, Italy as a Neo-Romantic painter and designer of theatrical sets and costumes for opera and ballet productions.
Eugene Berman was born on November 4, 1899 in St. Petersburg, Russia, the son of Lydia and Gustav Berman, who died when Eugene was seven years old. His stepfather was a wealthy banker who paid for his education in Germany, Switzerland, and France. In 1918, the family fled to Paris to escape the Bolshevik Revolution.
While in Paris, Berman studied at the Academie Ranson from 1920 to 1922, under Pierre Bonnard, Edouard Vuillard, and Félix Valloton. With his brother Leonid, Berman joined a group of painters who became known as Neo-Romantics whose paintings were of melancholy dreamlike scenes with mournful figures, defying the prevalent abstract movements in art. By the late 1920s, Berman was beginning to successfully sell his paintings and after meeting American gallery owner Julian Levy, he was offered an exhibition in New York. Berman continued to exhibit at the Julian Levy Gallery from 1929 to 1947.
In 1935, Eugene and Leonid Berman became war refugees and came to New York City. Eugene Berman designed covers for fashionable publications and by 1937, he was painting murals in private residences and designing sets and costumes for opera and ballet performances including those at the Metropolitan Opera.
Berman moved to California in 1938, settling in Los Angeles, and continued to paint murals and design for the theater. He became an American citizen in 1944. Between 1947 and 1949, he received Guggenheim Fellowships to obtain background images from the Southwest United States and Mexico for use in his art work. Berman married actress Ona Munson in 1949.
Two years after his wife's suicide in 1955, Berman moved to Rome, Italy where he continued to paint and design sets for the theater.
Eugene Berman died on December 14, 1972 in Rome, Italy.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of painter and theatrical set designer Eugene Berman date from 1926-1975 and measure 6.7 linear feet. Found within the papers are scattered letters, primarily postcards, from various colleagues including Juliet and Man Ray and Berman's brother Leonid. There are also notes, scattered artwork, printed material, and extensive photographs, many of Mexico.
Notes include a booklet of photocopies of notes in Italian conerning miscellaneous art work, including prices. There are also scattered notes in French concerning miscellaneous topics.
Art work consists of miscellaneous sketches, primarily on the reverse sides of postcards, depicting human figures and architectural details, sometimes annotated in Russian and Italian.
Printed material includes clippings concerning Eugene and Leonid Berman's art work, exhibition announcements and catalogs, reproductions of art work by Berman, picture postcards, a ballet program, and a guide book for Grado, Italy.
Photographs comprise the largest series in this collection. Photographs of Eugene Berman include two by Russell Lynes. Photographs are also of Berman's wife, Ona Munson, unidentified colleagues, exhibition installations, art work executed by Berman between 1937 and 1948, and miscellaneous photographs of Italy including images by Vincenzo Galdi and Wilhelm von Gloeden. There are ten portfolios of photographs of Mexico, primarily taken by Berman, but Portfolios 1, 6, 9, and 10 include images photographed by Hugo Brehme. There are also commercially produced photographs of various scenes and art work primarily in Italy and Mexico, publicity photographs of ballet and opera performers, and two stereographs of novelty subjects.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 5 series:
Series 1: Letters, 1926-1970 (Box 1, 8; 12 folders)
Series 2: Notes, 1944 (Box 1; 2 folders)
Series 3: Art Work, 1947 (Box 1; 2 folders)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1941-1975 (Box 1, 8; 1.5 linear feet)
Series 5: Photographs, 1933-1956 (Box, 2-9; 4.9 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Graphic artists; Painters -- California, Los Angeles; Painters -- Italy, Rome; Painters -- New York (State), New York; Set Designers
Subjects-Geographical:
Italy -- Description and travel, Photographs; Mexico -- Description and travel, Photographs
Types of Materials:
Notes; Photograph albums; Postcards; Sketches
Names:
Berman, Leonid, 1896-1976; Galdi, Vincenzo, photographer; Gloeden, Wilhelm von, Baron, 1856-1931, photographer; Lynes, Russell, 1910-1991; Ray, Man, 1890-1976
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Letters, 1926-1970, Series 1:; Box 1, 8; 12 folders)
  Scattered letters, consisting primarily of postcards, are from various colleagues including Matta, Juliet and Man Ray, and Berman's brother Leonid.
  - Correspondents with Unknown Surnames, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "A" - "M," undated, (Oversized Material Housed in Box 8) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "N" - "Z," undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1926-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters, 1946-1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters, 1950-1957 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters, 1962-1970, (Oversized Material Housed in Box 8) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Oversized Letter from Eugene Berman, undated, (from Box 1, Folder 2) (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Letter from Eugene Berman, 1962, from Box 1, Folder 11 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Notes, 1944, Series 2:; (Box 1; 2 folders)
  Notes consist of a booklet of photocopies of notes on miscellaneous art work, including prices. There are also scattered notes on miscellaneous topics.
  - Booklet of Photocopies of Notes on Art Work, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1944, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Art Work, 1947, Series 3:; (Box 1; 2 folders)
  Art work consists of miscellaneous sketches of human figures and architectural details.
  - Miscellaneous Sketches, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
- Printed Material, 1941-1975, Series 4:; (Box 1, 8; 1.5 linear feet)
  Printed material includes clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, reproductions of art work, picture postcards of scenes and art work found in various countries, and miscellaneous printed material.
  - Clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Clippings, 1949-1975 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1941-1949 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Exhibition Announcements for Leonid Berman, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Reproductions of Art Work by Berman, undated, (6 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 8) (Box 1, Folder 26-31)
  - Picture Postcard of Corsica, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Picture Postcard of Cuba (Havana), undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Picture Postcards of France, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Picture Postcards of Germany, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Picture Postcards of Great Britain, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Picture Postcard of Greece (Athens), undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Picture Postcards of Italy, undated, (50 folders) (Box 1, Folder 38-87)
  - Picture Postcards of Italy,undated, (6 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
  - Picture Postcards of Mexico, undated, (14 folders) (Box 2, Folder 7-20)
  - Picture Postcards of The Netherlands, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
  - Picture Postcards of Spain,undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Picture Postcard of Switzerland, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Picture Postcards of the United States, undated, (16 folders) (Box 2, Folder 25-40)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1950, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Oversized Reproductions of Art Work by Berman, undated, (from Box 1, Folder 30) (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Photographs, 1933-1956, Series 5:; (Box, 2-9; 4.9 linear feet)
  Photographs are of Eugene Berman (including ones taken by Russell Lynes), his wife, colleagues, exhibition installations, art work, and various travel locations. There are also commercially produced photographs of various scenes and art work primarily in Italy and Mexico, publicity photographs of ballet and opera performers, and stereographs of novelty subjects.
  - Photographs of Eugene Berman, 1935, undated, (Oversized Material housed in Box 8) (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Photographs of Ona Munson, Friends, and Colleagues, 1956, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Photographs of Exhibition Installations, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 44-46)
  - Portfolio "Photos of E. B. Paintings," 1948, (12 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 9) (Box 2, Folder 47-58)
  - Photographs of Miscellaneous Costume and Set Designs, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 59-61)
  - Photographs of Costume and Set Designs for Cosi Fan Tutti,1956, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 62-64)
  - Photographs of Art Work, undated, (7 folders) (Box 2, Folder 65-71)
  - Photographs of Art Work, undated, (9 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-9)
  - Photographs of Art Work Executed in 1937, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Art Work Executed in 1940, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Photographs of Art Work Executed in 1941, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
  - Photographs of Art Work Executed in 1942, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Photographs of Art Work Executed in 1943, undated, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 15-17)
  - Photographs of Art Work Executed in 1944, undated, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 18-20)
  - Photographs of Art Work Executed in 1945, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 21-22)
  - Photographs of Art Work Executed in 1947, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Photographs of Scenes in Italy, 1953, (13 folders) (Box 3, Folder 24-36)
  - Photographs of Scenes in Italy, 1956, (7 folders) (Box 3, Folder 37-43)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs of Scenes in Italy, undated, (15 folders) (Box 3, Folder 44-58)
  - Portfolio 1: Photographs of Mexico, undated, (10 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 9) (Box 3, Folder 59-68)
  - Portfolio 2: "Mexican Photos - Enlargements," 1947, (6 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 9) (Box 3, Folder 69-74)
  - Portfolio 3: "Mexican Photos - Enlargements," 1947, (7 folders)(Oversized Material Housed in Box 10) (Box 4, Folder 1-7)
  - Portfolio 4: "Mexican Photos," 1947, (4 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 10) (Box 4, Folder 8-11)
  - Portfolio 5: "Mexican Photos - Contact and Enlargement," 1947, (11 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 10) (Box 4, Folder 12-22)
  - Portfolio 6: "Mexican Photos - Instituto de los Monumentos Coloniales," undated, (10 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 10) (Box 4, Folder 23-32)
  - Portfolio 7: "Mexico Photographs for Ona," 1947, (7 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 10) (Box 4, Folder 33-39)
  - Portfolio 8: "Mexican Photos - Enlargements," 1947, (7 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 10) (Box 5, Folder 1-7)
  - Portfolio 9: "Mexican Photos - Brehme," 1947, undated, (Oversized Material Housed in Box 10) (Box 5, Folder 8-11)
  - Portfolio 10: "Mexican Photos - Instituto de los Monumentos Coloniales," undated, (9 folders) (Oversized Material Housed in Box 10) (Box 5, Folder 12-20)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs of Scenes in Mexico, 1947, undated, (6 folders) (Box 5, Folder 21-26)
  - Commercial Photographs of Scenes and Art Work in Austria, undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Commercial Photographs of Scenes and Art Work in France, undated, (4 folders) (Box 5, Folder 28-31)
  - Commercial Photographs of Scenes and Art Work in Great Britain, undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Commercial Photographs of Scenes and Art Work in Italy, undated, (30 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 9) (Box 5, Folder 33-62)
  - Commercial Photographs of Scenes and Art Work in Italy, undated, (22 folders) (Box 6, Folder 1-22)
  - Commercial Photographs of Scenes and Art Work in Italy, undated, (11 folders) (Box 7, Folder 1-11)
  - Commercial Photographs of Scenes and Art Work in Mexico, 1933, undated, (5 folders) (Box 7, Folder 12-16)
  - Commercial Photographs of Scenes and Art Work in Russia, undated (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Commercial Photographs of Scenes and Art Work in Spain, undated (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Commercial Photographs of Scenes and Art Work in the United States, undated, (4 folders) (Box 7, Folder 19-22)
  - Miscellaneous Commercial Photographs of Scenes and Art Work in Unidentified Locations, undated, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 23-24)
  - Photographs of Miscellaneous Ballet and Opera Performers, 1951, undated, (3 folders) (Box 7, Folder 25-27)
  - Stereographs of Novelty Subjects, undated (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Two Oversized Photographs of Eugene Berman by Russell Lynes, 1935, (from Box 2, Folder 42) (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Album of Photographs of Art Work, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Album of Photographs of Drawings of Mexico, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Cover for Portfolio "Photos of E. B. Paintings," 1948, (from Box 2, Folder 47) (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Oversized Cover for Portfolio 1: Photographs of Mexico, undated, (from Box 3, Folder 59) (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Cover for Portfolio 2: "Mexican Photos - Enlargements," 1947, (from Box 3, Folder 69) (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Portfolio of Miscellaneous Scenes in Mexico, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Four Oversized Commercial Photographs of Art Work in Italy (Florence), undated, (from Box 5, Folder 45) (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Oversized Cover for Portfolio 3: "Mexican Photos - Enlargements," 1947, (from Box 4, Folder 1) (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Cover for Portfolio 4: "Mexican Photos," 1947, (from Box 4, Folder 8) (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Cover for Portfolio 5: "Mexican Photos - Contact and Enlargement," 1947, (from Box 4, Folder 12) (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Oversized Cover for Portfolio 6: "Mexican Photos - Instituto de los Monumentos Coloniales," undated, (from Box 4, Folder 23) (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Oversized Cover for Portfolio 7: "Mexico Photographs for Ona," 1947, (from Box 4, Folder 33) (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Cover for Portfolio 8: "Mexican Photos - Enlargements," 1947, (from Box 5, Folder 1) (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Cover for Portfolio 9: "Mexican Photos - Brehme," 1947, undated, (from Box 5, Folder 8) (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Cover for Portfolio 10: "Mexican Photos - Instituto de los Monumentos Coloniales," undated, (from Box 5, Folder 12) (Box 10, Folder 4)